<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Short and true relation of intrigues transacted both at home and abroad to restore the late King James</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3557</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10572</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13783257</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13783257</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101790</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60052)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101790)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 850:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Short and true relation of intrigues transacted both at home and abroad to restore the late King James</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101790:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Short and True RELATION OF INTRIGUES TRANSACTED, Both at Home and Abroad, To Reſtore the Late King JAMES.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Virgil. AEneid. lib. 6.</bibl>
               <p>Facilis deſcenſus Averni, ſed revocare gradum hic labor, hoc opus eſt.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1694.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:101790:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101790:2"/>
            <head>A ſhort and true Relation of Intrigues tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted at Home and Abroad, to reſtore the late King <hi>James.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WE may ſee, by the overturn of the late King, the Inſtability of Human Greatneſs; and that Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty is like the Globe of the Earth, full of Windings and Turnings, having its Ebbs and Flows like the Ocean, which never reſts, and which ſhews Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be a ſlippery Path; for if the Prince chance to catch a Fall, though ſuch a Miſhap may not prove Mortal, yet it ſo diſables him ever after, that he cannot recover himſelf: Which at this time ſeems verified in the Fall of the late King, who now finds himſelf miſtaken in his Meaſures, which renders all his Endeavours frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and turns to no other Account, but to fruſtrate his Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and to remove his Hopes from ever aſcending the Engliſh Throne again.</p>
            <p>The Nobles and Commons in Parliament aſſembled, after the late King's Coronation, demonſtrated their Fidelity to him, by their unexpected Attainder of the late Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> who but a little before was the Peoples Darling, and yet notwithſtanding was ſacrificed for the preſervation of the late King; an Inſtance of ſo much Integrity at that Juncture of Time, when the late King dreaded nothing more than the Landing of the Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> that if the late King had but eſteemed the Affection of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, purſuant to the Experience he had then of their Loyalty, and retained the ſame, and contained himſelf within the Rules of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration in point of good Government, and not openly exceeded the Limits of the Law, and ſtrove to content the People, which is the End of all good Government, a Duty incumbent upon Kings and Princes to do, he might have Ruled and Reigned to this Day, and all the Days of his natural Life, with as much Honour, Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur and Satisfaction, as any Prince that ever reigned in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101790:3"/>
            <p>The late King had more Experience in Government than any Prince that came before him. He had ſeen the Tragical Fate of his Father's Death, the Turnings and Windings in his late Brother's Reign, wherein he himſelf had an ample Share every way; and was fifty two years a Subject before he came to be King: So that it might be expected from a Prince of his Knowledg and Years, to rule well, and to fulfil that Saying of <hi>Maecenas</hi> to <hi>Auguſtus, Nemo bene Imperat niſi qui ante paruerit Imperio.</hi> Whereas had the late King but kept the Reins of his Government equal in his Hand, ſo as to be able to have made a Judgment when to drive faſt or ſlow, and between both had kept a middling Pace, and by an impartial diſtribution of Juſtice pleaſed the lower Orb, and truſted not too far to corrupted Miniſters and Judges, who are the Plagues of all Governments, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Cicero, Acceptatio munerum eſt praevaricatio Juſtitiae &amp; Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis,</hi> he had been now, inſtead of a Depoſed Prince in a Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Land, happy at Home. But now he can tell, that a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple can do better without a King, than a King without a People; and as nothing would have pleaſed his Ambition but to trample up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Liberties and Privileges of his Subjects, ſo the Subjects thought themſelves obliged to let him know, that the Affection of the People is the ſureſt Foundation of Government, by their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring their averſion to the late King, and ſeating the preſent King and Queen upon the Throne.</p>
            <p>The late King thought to imitate <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8th</hi> the contrary way, but came ſhort of his Undertaking, and loſing the Love of his People, loſt himſelf and three Kingdoms. <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8th</hi> fought the Pope at his own Weapons, pick'd his Locks with his own Keys, lock'd in the Supremacy, and ſhut out the Pope: And for his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conds, had the two great Convocations of Roman Catholick Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines then reſiding in both the Univerſities of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridg,</hi> together with all the Monaſtical and Collegiat Theologues through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole Kingdom; which beſpeaks the Engliſh Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, both at <hi>Rome</hi> and all Abroad, very ſcandalous, having no Reputation nor Eſteem any where out of <hi>England,</hi> but hated mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally.</p>
            <p>The late King to oblige the Pope, and out of his fervent Zeal to Religion likewiſe, went about to alter the Caſe, and to remove the Aſperſion, wherewith all the Engliſh Roman Catholicks are brand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and fix it upon Engliſh Proteſtants, when he with a Proteſtant Army attempted to eſtabliſh Popery, againſt Law, in a Proteſtant
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101790:3"/>Kingdom, and to extirpate the Proteſtant Religion. An Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking too dangerous (as it fell out) to be attempted; and no wonder it ſhould, when a Prince, againſt all the Rules of Religious Policy, and contrary to good Conduct in point of good Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, without any more neceſſity to compel him than his Ambition and Zeal, to take ſuch Meaſures as would not only incenſe the People againſt him, and inflame three Kingdoms, but alſo entail an Inteſtine War upon the Kingdom: For St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> a great Doctor in the Church, as well as in the Politicks, ſays, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mota juſtitia, &amp; quid ſunt Regna, ſed magna Latrocinia?</hi> the remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Religion and Juſtice, lets in an Inundation of Sorrow, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity, and Diſtreſs, to the overthrow of all good Law and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Honeſty; which the late King now ſees, when inſtead of being attended by his Nobles, Miniſters, and his Judges, and ſeated at Home upon the Throne, he himſelf, with the help of his more than corrupted Council, brought all upon himſelf, and is neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be maintained at the Expence of another Prince: which ſhews the Uncertainty, as well as the Infelicity of humane Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to ſee a Prince that might have been happy, but would not, and now inſtead of Ruling and Commanding his late great Officers, is again glad to receive and liſten to the meaneſt of his late Subjects: A Prince that would not hear the Counſel of the Wiſe, but embraced the Advice of Fools, is accordingly accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; who expected by his Exile, when he left his People, to return Triumphantly an abſolute Monarch, as he thought; but ſo far from it at this time, that that Prince from whom he expected Succour, has enough to do to defend himſelf, being ſurrounded by many Enemies, which leaves the late King no hopes of Supply there, having to that purpoſe received the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Anſwer but in <hi>February</hi> laſt, which crown'd all the late King's Misfortunes with additional Sorrow, as preſently will appear.</p>
            <p>The late King hath no other Remedy left him, as the Caſe ſtands now Abroad, but to court his late injured People to bring him back again; which is not ſo eaſily to be comprehended: That Prince muſt be reduced to great Hardſhips, that firſt receives a broken Head, and petitions him that gave it for a Plaiſter, it looks as if no other was or is to be had: But wo be to him that takes that Meaſure for his Redreſs.</p>
            <p>The late King believes that the ſame People that betrayed and deſerted him, may be prevailed with by his Declarations and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101790:4"/>to reſtore him again. But, God comfort him! he is miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken; the Caſe is ſince altered, and thoſe Religious Weather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocks, upon whoſe Promiſes he does (at this time) depend, are as Impotent to do him any Good, as they were Potent to ruin him when here laſt; they have not that Virtue that's ſaid to be in <hi>Achilles</hi>'s Spear, they gave the mortal Wound, but they cannot heal it now they would, being out of their reach.</p>
            <p>And the late King expecting they could, to pleaſe them, hath excluded the Proteſtant Diſſenters, and the Roman Catholicks of <hi>Ireland,</hi> both innocent of the Misfortunes that juſtly overtook him; and is ſo conſcientious, that he condemns the Innocent, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons the Nocent, when he offers all the Proteſtant Diſſenters and the Roman Catholicks of <hi>Ireland,</hi> (the latter having been Sufferers with a Vengeance in his Cauſe) as an Oblation to the <hi>Paſſive-Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> Men, who infuſed Non-reſiſtance into the late Army: And now theſe are the late King's Creatures, and the only Perſons that would abdicate the Goſpel, as they did their Paſſive-Obedience King, rather than the Church-Livings.</p>
            <p>The late King fulfils the true Character of his Family in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that have been all known to be unconſtant, and unfaithful to their Friends, and liberal and grateful to their Foes. But God has accordingly dealt with them, he has raiſed them a multitude of Enemies, and left the Succeſſion of this Crown (without any Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conds) to fight its Battel: And if it be remembred how that the late King, and his Brother <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, after their return, from Exile, treated the decayed Cavaliers, who loſt their All in their Cauſe, it ſhould leave him deſtitute of Friends. And if it be alſo conſidered how many Noblemen and Gentlemen, that ſpent their Eſtates and Fortunes in the Defence of the Succeſſion of this Crown, and how they were rewarded by King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, and by the late King, having received for their Comforts in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, petitioning about <hi>White-hall,</hi> nothing but Sham-Referen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the Treaſury, and paid in cold Waiting, long Attendance, Tricks, Diſappointments, Promiſes and Delays, that betwixt King-Craft, and Court-Cheats, and Sharpers, Perſons of unqueſtionable Families, unſpotted Loyalty, and Sufferers in abundance, have fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed for Hunger, and periſhed with Cold, and their Poſterity to this Day left without any Satisfaction, and reduced to a very mean and low Condition; which ſhould take away the leaſt Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101790:4"/>from all Perſons to intermeddle in the late King's Cauſe, but look upon his Fall, and the overthrow of his Crown, a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due to the Family, and may ſay; <hi>Juſtus es Deus, &amp; juſtum eſt Judicium tuum.</hi> It would be a pity indeed that all the Family ſhould depart this World, till they, or ſome of them, atone for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold Abominations wherewithal they ſtand charged here, as well as before the Great Tribunal, for what Evils they have committed againſt their People.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> although in Point of Intereſt and Perſwaſion different from us, yet to do them Right, have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved well from the late King, though ill from us; and for the late King to leave them and exclude them, is ſuch an Inſtance of mean Ingratitude, that Proteſtants have no reaſon to ſtand by a Prince that deſerts his own Party, and a People that have been faithful to him and his Intereſt to the very laſt. That they were overcome, is not ſo much to be wondered at, as their holding out againſt the Power and Wealth of <hi>England,</hi> and againſt all Nations to admiration ſo long as they did, and at laſt to force ſuch Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from us, as ſhould render them a People never to be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the Succeſſors of this Crown: but King <hi>James</hi> is the late un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable King <hi>James</hi> ſtill, a King that is not to be found but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Uncertainty. What have the <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters</hi> done to him, that he has in the Articles of <hi>September</hi> laſt excluded them? They had no hand in Undermining, Betraying, nor Deſerting of him, they have carried themſelves obedient to his lawful Commands; and becauſe they did ſo, he, contrary to all his Pretenſions of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Zeal for Liberty of Conſcience, by his Exceptions in the ſaid Articles, expoſes them all to Ruin and Deſtruction; that is to ſay, when he returns. But when the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> conſider how he deſerts thoſe of his own Religion, they may content themſelves with being as they are, out of the reach of his Hatred; and ſeeing that his Favours are only reſerved to promote his Enemies, and that he has loſt all Abroad, let his Enemies grow potent every where, and numerous withal, and let him be ſo loſt, that he may never be found here at Home.</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing the late King hath expoſed himſelf, by excluding a People that never prejudiced him nor his Intereſt, to gratify the Deſires of thoſe that have turned him out of all: It is hop'd, that as he had the pleaſure of Excepting, that he will give leave to return him a <hi>Quid</hi> for his <hi>Quo,</hi> by directing ſuch Meaſures, as may
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101790:5"/>anticipate all his throughout <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and by intimating to the Government ſuch a Method as may for the future detect all the Devices on foot in order to his Reſtauration, and ſo have his Exceptions by his own Excluſion executed.</p>
            <p>The following Relation, as had from Gentlemen of very good Note, who have ſeen moſt of the Tranſactions at St. <hi>Germains</hi> for about four Years laſt paſt, gives a very impartial Account of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and ſhews the Connexion of Foreign and Domeſtick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues, carried on and managed with reſtleſs Induſtry now for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two Years laſt paſt, in order to the Reſtauration of the late King; which at laſt turned to no better Account, than to put a Period to his Expectations, by leaving him but ſmall or no Hopes to return ever again, as will plainly appear; the Truth whereof will want no Confirmation, for farther enquiry into Foreign Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs will remove all Doubts, and leave no room for Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
            <p>ABOUT two Years ſince the late King had great hopes to be reſtored with Triumph, and fed himſelf with the thoughts of being an abſolute Monarch, having about that Time received great Encouragement, as well from the <hi>Pope</hi> as from the <hi>French</hi> King, which made him look above the Reach of his late Subjects, (as he thought) and to reject all my Lord <hi>Preſton</hi>'s Undertakings, and the reſt concerned in that Intrigue; which was like to have coſt my Lord <hi>Preſton</hi> his Life, and for which he had no Thanks, but on the contrary was deſpiſed for meddling; the late King proteſting then, that he had rather never ſee <hi>England,</hi> than come to treat or capitulate with his Subjects again: But he ſoon altered his Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſeeing Affairs Abroad thwart his Deſigns; and meeting with ſuch unexpected Diſappointments, which abated much of the Thoughts he retained but a little before; ſo that of a ſudden Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he with great Impatience conſulted ſome of his Proteſtant Council, telling them that he was reſolved to treat with his late Subjects, and give them any Conditions rather than ſtand out any longer, concluding that nothing would more conduce to his Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, than to reconcile himſelf to his late Subjects.</p>
            <p>In order thereto an Expreſs was ſent to <hi>England,</hi> with Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to my Lord <hi>Middleton</hi> and ſome others, to treat with the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to know their Inclinations by feeling how their Pulſes beat, and accordingly to proceed: Which my Lord <hi>Middleton</hi> did,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101790:5"/>and drew a Declaration anſwerable to the Deſires of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſome other Heads of both the Kingdoms: And after ſome Debates, my Lord <hi>Middleton</hi> went away for <hi>France,</hi> and arrived at St. <hi>Germains</hi> the beginning of <hi>March,</hi> or thereabouts, 1692/3; produced the Declaration, which admitted of high Debates, and long Arguments <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> as their ſeveral ſeparate Intereſts moved the Miniſters of St. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains:</hi> But my Lord <hi>Melford</hi> ſtarted ſeveral Caſes of Conſcience againſt the late King's ſigning the ſaid Declaration; inſomuch that to be ſatisfied therein, and to remove all Scruples of Conſcience, the late King conſulted the College of <hi>Sorbon,</hi> and the Iriſh Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege likewiſe. The Faculty of <hi>Sorbon</hi> declared againſt the ſaid Declaration, and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> College for it.</p>
            <p>The Iriſh College gave theſe Reaſons, That the King was in Exile, baniſhed his Kingdoms by his own Children and Subjects for his Religion; that as the Caſe ſtood with him, there was no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for his Reſtauration left him, but to comply with his Subjects, and to ſign any Inſtrument whatever, for to prevail with them to accept of him home again; and whatever he ſhould ſign whilſt in Exile, and under Tribulation abroad, he ſhould not in Conſcience be obliged to perform after his Reſtauration, as exacted from him <hi>per</hi> Force and Dureſs; which renders all Conditions and Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of that kind, neither obligatory nor binding, any longer than a fit Opportunity ſhould offer it ſelf to break them; [and wherein he would but imitate his Brother <hi>Charles</hi> II. who took the Covenant in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and after his Reſtauration burnt it at <hi>London,</hi> by the hands of the Common Hangman.] The Faculty of <hi>Sorbon</hi> declared againſt this kind of Machiavelian Doctrine, and againſt the Declaration too: Yet notwithſtanding the late King did ſign the ſaid Declaration on the Conſideration aforeſaid. But my Lord <hi>Melford</hi> and my Lord <hi>Middleton</hi> fell out, and are to this day irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilable; they do not contend for any Good either of them would do to this Side or that Side, but their Quarrel is like that of <hi>Ceſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey,</hi> who ſhould be the <hi>Greateſt,</hi> not the <hi>Beſt:</hi> But <hi>Melford</hi> (a Convert in Wolves Dreſs, under the ſhadow of Religion) bears the Sway, <hi>Tantum Religio potuit ſuadere malorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſaid Declaration ſo ſigned by the late King, was ordered to be ſent into <hi>Flanders</hi> to be read there at the Head of the Iriſh Troops; but was to them the moſt unwelcome and unacceptable Meſſage that ever they met withal, or that the late King could ſend
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101790:6"/>them, finding by the ſaid Declaration, that they loſt themſelves both at Home and Abroad, by the late King; which cauſed ſuch a Conſternation in the Camp, that the Souldiers (who would be glad of any Occaſion to quit the Service and to return Home) openly mutinied; having ſtarted the Queſtion, that now being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted by King <hi>James,</hi> why ſhould they not go over to King <hi>William</hi> and accept of Conditions? But the Queſtion was carried in the Negative, and an Expreſs ſent immediately to St. <hi>Germains,</hi> to let the late King know the Diſcontent amongſt the Souldiers, and the Diſorder in the Camp occaſioned by the ſaid Declaration. Here K. <hi>James</hi> returns to himſelf again, and after his old Cuſtom of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Undoing, gets another Declaration drawn, ſigns the ſame, to null the former, and ſends away two Gentlemen and two Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gymen of Note with this new Declaration for <hi>Flanders,</hi> to pacify the Iriſh, and to give them Content; which for ſome Days gave ſome Satisfaction, but not ſo much as to harbour a good Thought of the late King, believing that if ever he ſhould be reſtored, they would be all loſt through his Unconſtancy; and that by repoſing their Truſt in him, they confided in a rotten Reed: but however they were appeaſed for that time.</p>
            <p>Here the late King, forgetting his laſt Declaration and Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Iriſh, ſends the firſt Declaration for <hi>England</hi> without any Amendment, or taking any notice of the laſt Declaration to the Iriſh; but with the former Exception againſt them, he lets it paſs for <hi>England.</hi> Here (as they relate it Abroad) it was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed the 19th of <hi>May</hi> laſt; but ſeveral not believing the ſame to be the late King's Declaration, but the Product of ſome other Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to amuſe the People, ſeem'd diſguſted at it, and would give it no Credit: But that the People may be undeceived in the ſaid Declaration, notice was ſent to St. <hi>Germains</hi> what the People ſaid about it; and immediately to remove all Doubts touching the ſame, the late King cauſed it to be put in the <hi>Paris</hi> Gazette, where (to his great Diſhonour and Diſadvantage) it was publiſhed by Authority, which gave Content in <hi>England,</hi> and great Diſcontent to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army, who are ever ſince in great diſorder about it: but the King of <hi>France</hi> has promiſed to ſee them righted, who are all very unruly and weary of King <hi>James,</hi> (except ſome Officers, that cannot live ſo well at Home as in their Station Abroad) and willing to quit the Service upon any reaſonable Conditions what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; eſpecially the common Souldiers, who are extraordinary
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101790:6"/>poor and diſſatisfied, would give any thing to be at Home.</p>
            <p>The Nobility and Gentry of <hi>France</hi> finding a Declaration of King <hi>James</hi>'s in the <hi>Paris</hi> Gazette, were ſurprized at it; and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him deſert the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Intereſt, did look upon it as very great Unconſtancy of Reſolution, which in truth removed the Intereſt and Affection of the Clergy and Nobility of <hi>France</hi> from him, who, before that Publication, were all reſolved for him, and to promote his Reſtauration to their Power; but ſince are grown cold upon the Matter, and but indifferent whether he be reſtored or not. In the Court of <hi>France</hi> the late King is extreamly much made of; but had he more Conſtancy of Mind, he would be much better looked upon there, where nothing elſe but Reſolution is in Eſteem.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Declaration, it ſeems, had ſuch Effects, that ſome have been pleaſed to ſend away a Draught of Articles or Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, contained, as reported from abroad, under twelve Heads, which the late King, in farther confirmation of his good Will to that Party he relies on, hath in <hi>September</hi> laſt ſigned, as they ſay that came from thence. Since the return of the ſaid Articles for <hi>England</hi> ſigned, they ſay abroad, that Preparations have been dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently uſed for the Reſtoration of the late King.</p>
            <p>And that in <hi>December</hi> laſt an Expreſs arrived from <hi>England</hi> at <hi>St. Germains,</hi> which gave the ſatisfactory account of the Peoples return to their former Allegiance to King <hi>James:</hi> how true or falſe it was, that Court was ſo elevated with Joy, that nothing was talked off, but an immediate Return for <hi>England,</hi> all there ſtriving who ſhould be foremoſt upon the Expedition others, to make ſome conſiderable Figure, came away, as they ſay, to have ſome Men in readineſs againſt the Landing here in <hi>England.</hi> Frequent freſh News came from <hi>England,</hi> confirming the ſame; and every half-ſtarved poor Man about Court uſed his Intereſt to have ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Imployment; and he that could not be in a valuable Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, thought himſelf as good as loſt: by which we may judg how the Jacobites here in <hi>England</hi> would be look'd on. But it's thought the late King would continue his Favour to them, by leaving them always reſerved to drink his Health, an Imployment moſt ſutable to their Principles; for certainly they that live in ſo merry a Mode in his Abſence, cannot but do extraordinary well when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns, that is to ſay, if their Money holds out, otherwiſe they may become <hi>Williamites.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:101790:7"/>
            <p>About this time <hi>France</hi> was as full of the Expectation of a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Peace to be concluded all abroad, as other Places were full of the Rumour thereof; and to ſtay for the Ratification, was alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be the only ſtop that prolonged the late King's coming away, having all things at Home and Abroad ready, doubting not in the leaſt but all things would have anſwered Expectation. But all the Preparations returned to nothing, and the great Joy, of a ſudden, to Sorrow, inſomuch that all the Tidings at Home and Abroad met together, in the Diſſolution of the Hopes of a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Reſtoration.</p>
            <p>The late King having about the fourth Day of <hi>February</hi> laſt, New Stile, acquainted the French King with the frequent good Tidings from his late Subjects, who now were returned to their Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and all free to hazard their Lives and Fortunes for his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, which he ſaid, were all true according to his Intelligence, and that he was moſt certain and ſure that none would oppoſe him in <hi>England;</hi> the French King told him, that he was glad to hear it, and wiſhed it might prove ſo, but ſeem'd to give little Credit to it.</p>
            <p>The late King preſſed hard to have ſome Succours to come for <hi>England</hi> the beginning of laſt <hi>March,</hi> but ſtill the French King doubted the Reality of the Engliſh to him, alledging thus, as King <hi>James</hi> repeated the ſame after his return from <hi>Verſailles</hi> to St. <hi>Germains:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, ſays the French King, as you have experience to know your Subjects, ſo I know them by their Character, and do believe them to be a People of no Faith, no Honour, and no Honeſty, whom no Promiſe can oblige, nor Oath can bind: And as for their Clergy, I look upon them much worſe than the Commonalty, having not only by Teaching and Preaching taught the People to forſwear themſelves, but ſhewed ill Examples in themſelves by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame; they have ſworn Allegiance to you, and ſince ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> for their King, and ſwear Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to him; how this Swearing to both can be reconciled, I cannot underſtand: But let them ſwear what they will, I ſhould not believe them, nor put any more value upon their Oath than they do themſelves, which is nothing at all. Neither do I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand how you can be aſſured of them that have no other Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to give you of their future Fidelity but their Oaths, which are worth as much now, as when they broke with your Majeſty
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101790:7"/>laſt; it is out of my reach to put any Truſt in ſuch People, neither would I have you confide in them, for I doubt much their Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity; and if they are weary of the War at a Diſtance, what will they not be when it's with them at Home? that will be your time to hear them, and not before.</p>
            <p>The late King ſtill urged to come for <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupon the French King told him, ſeeing he had that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in his Subjects, that if they did but demonſtrate their Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity by ſome Action, as the ſeizing of any Citadel, Town or Fore of any good Conſequence, and put ſuch in his Hands as might be for the Safety of his Ships, and ſecure the landing of an Army; that after that was effectually done, he would give him Succours; but before, he did not think it ſafe to venture, conſidering how his own Affairs ſtood at Home and Abroad. The late King preſſed no further upon him, but returned to St. <hi>Germains,</hi> where he told all the Particulars, which put that Court into ſuch a Fit of Grief and Sorrow, that they were all like ſo many People going to die. In five days after, all the decayed Gentlemen about Court were ordered ſome Advance-Money upon their Penſions, and commanded Homeward, to make the beſt of their Way and Conditions, who are now upon the Road for <hi>Flanders,</hi> others coming for <hi>England,</hi> and the reſt begging all along, being in a moſt deplorable Condition.</p>
            <p>The Engliſh Proteſtants about that Court do wiſh themſelves at Home again, for there they are reſpected as Strangers, but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as Proteſtants, and looked upon as Spies from <hi>England;</hi> ſo are ſome Roman Catholicks too, who thereupon, both Clergy and Laity, were forbid the Court.</p>
            <p>The Proteſtants are hated likewiſe by the People there, who have the ſame Notion of Religion, if not with more Zeal, as the People here: The Proteſtants are under the Calumnies of the late King's Declaration, and the Articles both againſt Roman Catholicks and Diſſenters; and the Engliſh Proteſtants about Court on that account are loathed and hated by the People there, who are full of it: For Engliſh Proteſtants to go for <hi>France,</hi> to propagate their Religion, where a Native Proteſtant cannot live, is but like the Quakers that went to <hi>Rome</hi> to reconcile the Pope to be a Quaker; they are equally looked upon, though not equally treated; the Quakers were looked upon in <hi>Rome</hi> to be mad Men, and were ſent to <hi>Bedlam,</hi> but our Engliſh Proteſtants are yet at
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101790:8"/>Liberty, and in more danger of the <hi>Baſtile</hi> than of <hi>Bedlam,</hi> being of late upon their Good-behaviour, but ſtill much ſuſpected.</p>
            <p>The late King did all along rely upon the Pope's Intereſt to mediate a Peace Abroad, and addreſſed a great many other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the ſame purpoſe, hoping that a Peace Abroad would be a means to bring him to his late Home: The Pope did uſe his Intereſt that way, and ſo did the Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> but it was to no Effect; for no Body ſeem'd willing but the French King to accept of the Peace, which in him was but to wheedle ſome of the Confederate Princes to liſten to his Propoſals, and accept of his Conditions, to divide and break the Allies, and that ſo by taking off ſome, and diſperſing their Forces, he may with the more Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility cruſh the reſt, and break all at laſt: But the Confederates who are ſenſible of his Deſigns, will accept of no Conditions from him of his own Propoſals, but intend to bring him to their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions; they all foreſee that he intends to become Emperor of the Weſt, which he cannot attain to, but in conſequence muſt extirpate the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> in whoſe Preſervation all the Princes think themſelves obliged to keep up the War, rather than voluntarily ſuffer themſelves to be brought under a Yoke of Tyranny and Uſurpation.</p>
            <p>The Emperor is well ſatisfied, that the War made by the Grand Seignior againſt the Empire, was promoted by the French King, and ſince furthered by him; which conſideration requires the Emperor to decline all his Propoſals until the French King firſt allays that War raiſed by himſelf upon the Emperor. As for the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> the French King is a Plague to him by ravaging of his Territories, ſeizing his Towns and Forts, without any pretence of Juſtice, and compelling his Subjects to ſwear Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to him by the Law of Conqueſt, which by Divine Law is no Lawful Right, but a Homicide and open Robbery; for Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind was free in the beginning, but ſince by the Power of Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation ſubjected under a Yoke, which loſt the World forty times over more Lives, to continue and maintain Man's Ambition over Man, than are left living in the World: therefore as God's Laws are againſt deſtroying and killing of Men, certainly that Power which cannot govern nor live, but upon the deſtruction of God's Creation, cannot be called Juſt nor Lawful <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> but an abſolute Tyranny; though ſome of our Divines will ſay that a Conqueſt is a Lawful Title, ſo it is by the Law of the Sword, but againſt the Law of Natural Right.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:101790:8"/>
            <p>Some perhaps may take occaſion to queſtion, by what Law did King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> aſcend this Throne? A Queſtion as ſoon anſwered, By a better Title than ever <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, or <hi>Julius Ceſar</hi> had to any Part of their ſeveral Conqueſts. K. <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> had the Choice and Affection of the People, which is the beſt Foundation, and ſureſt Title that ever Prince had to build upon, and without which no Prince can be ſafe on the Throne. But that Prince that has it, and knows how to keep it, and retains it, may reign and rule in defiance of all Foreign Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; if it does not happen to him to have a corrupted Council, which is the overthrow of any State, Kingdom or Empire. We need not go Abroad for Precedents, having ſome of the Council at Home in being, that brought us almoſt to Deſtruction, and are as likely to do it once again as ever they did before, if God prevents not. It is true enough, that where a Prince has not an Army to rule abſolutely, no King of <hi>England</hi> can hurt the Privileges of the Subjects, if his Miniſters and Judges be but faithful to the Prince and People, in diſcharge of their Truſt according to Law; but otherwiſe all goes to wrack.</p>
            <p>We exclaim againſt the late King's Evil Counſellors, and who can ſay that there was one good amongſt them? It is commonly ſaid, that they that have betray'd the Secrets of one King againſt the Oaths commonly taken, have ſince betrayed another: Or how can this King and Queen believe themſelves happy in the Counſel of thoſe, whom they themſelves know to have been falſe to the late King? Or is it to be thought the Kingdom is aſleep, when a Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour is raiſed againſt the late King's Evil Counſellors, when at the ſame time the major Part of them are ſtill in our Councils and Places of Truſt? which denotes a long Snake in the Graſs. But I ſhall do by them as God Almighty did, leave them, and return to conclude my Diſcourſe; only adding, that the Court of St. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains</hi> dreads nothing more than ſuch an Alteration of the Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy and Juſtices of Peace over all <hi>England,</hi> as it has pleaſed their Majeſties of late to cauſe in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reſolution of the Confederates againſt the Peace, has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the Meaſures of <hi>France,</hi> aboliſhed the Thoughts of a Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and has put a Period to all the Deſigns of an Invaſion from <hi>France</hi> hither. It is of all hands in <hi>France</hi> believed, that thrô the Diſtraction amongſt the Clergy and Gentry about the Taxes, the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101790:9"/>ſcarcity of Money among the Commonalty, with the want of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, and the exceſſive Expences of the War to maintain ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Armies, the Glory of that Crown, without a Peace, cannot hold much longer; the declination of the Wealth of <hi>France</hi> having reduced all People to a very low Ebb.</p>
            <p>And if the late King and the French King did hold a Reſolution to land an Army in this Kingdom, this Iſland is ſo naturally ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſituated, that they would find it a difficult Matter to land an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my here, having the Elements to fight with, and the Sea to conquer, before they can touch the Shore: and perhaps the Attempt, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever tried, may prove as fatal to <hi>France,</hi> as the overthrow of the Spaniſh Armado was to <hi>Spain.</hi> Which makes me think of <hi>Hegeſip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> who perſonated King <hi>Agrippa,</hi> in his Diſcourſe to <hi>Claudius</hi> of the Danger and Difficulty of invading <hi>Great Britain;</hi> which Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ended, as <hi>Florus</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Ligurians,</hi> and as I may ſay and conclude,</p>
            <q>Major labor eſt invenire, quam vincere.</q>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Mr. <hi>Waller.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <l>'Tis not ſo hard, for greedy Foes to ſpoil</l>
                  <l>Another Nation, as to touch our Soil.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
